<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true souldiers convoy A sermon preached upon the xvjth. day of May 1640, vpon a prayer day, for the Princes good successe in going forth to warre. By William Bridge.</title>
            <author>Bridge, William, 1600?-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16830</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3732</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106547</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842261</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842261</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6902</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16830)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6902)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1129:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true souldiers convoy A sermon preached upon the xvjth. day of May 1640, vpon a prayer day, for the Princes good successe in going forth to warre. By William Bridge.</title>
                  <author>Bridge, William, 1600?-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>110 [i.e. 100], [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Lappagde and are to be sold at his house on the Iron Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>In Rotterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>P. 100 misnumbered 110.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6902:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6902:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The true Souldiers Convoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon preached upon the xvj<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. day of May 1640, vpon a prayer day, for the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces good ſucceſſe in going forth to warre.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM BRIDGE.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Thou haſt broken Rahab in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as one that is ſlaine, thou haſt ſcattered thine enemies with thy ſtrong arme.</hi> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 10.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>IN ROTTERDAM.</p>
            <p>Printed for Thomas Lippagde and are to be ſold at his houſe on the Iron Bridge, 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:6902:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>REader; out of deſire to the good of Gods people, and in reſpect of theſe trouble-ſome times, it was thought not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unfit by ſome friends, to print theſe few notes, in reading of which thou art deſired not to expect much compleatnes of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency or ſtile, as not being or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to the preſſe by the author himſelfe, but by a very weake hand: whatſoeuer therfore thou shalt find herein profitable, that improue: if any thing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, that couer by Chriſtian loue and the God of loue be with thee Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:6902:2"/>
            <head>Numbers cha: 10. the middle of the 35 verſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Riſe up O Lord and let thine enemies be ſcattered.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His chap. delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it ſelfe into foure parts.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the <hi>Firſt</hi> part the Author ſpeaketh of the ſilver Trumpets and of the matter and uſe of them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Secondly</hi> he ſheweth the march of the children of Iſrael under their ſeuerall ſtandards.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Thirdly</hi> he ſpeaketh of a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6902:3"/> conference had betweene Moſes and Hobab <hi>verſ.</hi> 29.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>Fourthly</hi> you haue Moſes prayer: <hi>And they departed from the mount verſ.</hi> 33. <hi>and the Arke of the couenant of the Lord went before them in the three dayes iourney, &amp;c: And it came to paſſe when the Arke ſet forward, that Moſes ſaide, Riſe up O Lord and let thine enemies be ſcattered,</hi> when they remoued ſtill they prayed, when they ſett forth with their army, they uſed thoſe words: <hi>Ariſe O Lord &amp; let thine enemies be ſcattered:</hi> when they returned with their army at the latter end of the yeere, or at any time, they ſaide, <hi>Returne O Lord unto the many thouſands of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You haue here their going forth, ariſe O Lord &amp;c &amp; it is as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6902:3"/> if hee had ſayd thus: O Lord thou haſt promiſed thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence to thy people and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou haſt giuen them thine Arke, the outward ſigne of thy preſence, now we are to goe forth to warre, and that is a dangerous worke, oh let us not goe alone without thee, but let us haue thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, wherefore <hi>ariſe O Lord and let thine enemies be ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered;</hi> He doth not ſay thus, O Lord we entreate thee, giue us good munition or good prouiſion, or (that which the world calleth the nerues of wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re) giue us money, but as if he would ſhew that Gods preſence is moſt deſireable to an army, &amp; that Gods preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is their munition and proviſion and containeth all things, he ſaith <hi>Ariſe O Lord</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:6902:4"/>
            <p> Theſe words containe ſome thing implyed, and ſomething expreſſed: implied two things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Firſt</hi> that God hath ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that ſeems to be granted.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Secondly</hi> that God ſleepeth to his enemies, therefore hee ſaith ariſe, theſe implied: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed three things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Firſt</hi> the matter of the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that is that God would ariſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Secondly</hi> the effect of Gods riſing, that his enemies may be ſcattered.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Thirdly</hi> the occaſion of this petition, that is <hi>their going forth to warre: from theſe</hi> wordes, <hi>then Moſes ſaid</hi> Accordingly there are f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue notes or obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that I intend (God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) to run through at thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:6902:4"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Firſt that God himſelfe hath many enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Secondly as God hath ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſoe ſometime he ſleepeth to all their enmitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Thirdly though God ſleepeth and they worke, yet there is a time when they ſhall be ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and when God ariſeth, they are ſcattered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>Fourthly our prayers awaken God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>Fiftly, when the people of the land goe forth to warre, Gods people ſhould go forth to prayer</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Firſt, God himſelfe hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny enemies,</hi> Let none wonder at this, nay rather wonder that God hath any friendes in the world it is ſo wicked, the Scripture is full for it, in that Pſal. 8: verſ. 2. <hi>Out of the mouthes of babes and ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings haſt thou ordained ſtrength</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:6902:5"/> 
               <hi>becauſe of thine enemies. Pſal</hi> 37. 20. <hi>But the wicked ſhall periſh and the enemies of the Lord ſhall be as the fat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of lambes. Pſal.</hi> 74. 4. <hi>Thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies roare,</hi> &amp;c. Ye know the Pſal. <hi>For loe thine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nemies O Lord, for loe thine enemies.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 9</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Rea</hi> 1. Thoſe that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in league and covenant one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, haue common friends &amp; common enemies. Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are in covenant with God, and therefore they having ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, God hath enemies,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ </seg>2</label> 2 There is a ſpecial contrariety betweene God &amp; the world, <hi>the flesh luſteth againſt the ſpirit and the ſpirit against th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 17.</note> 
               <hi>flesh, for they are contrarie:</hi> take but this one inſtance in this matter of contrariety, to ſee how contrary God and the godly are to the Deuill and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6902:5"/> the wicked. Let a thing be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo bad, God and the godly will turne it to good and Gods honour: Let a thing be never ſoe good, the Deuill and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men will turne it to bad and Gods diſhonour: now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity being nothing els but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livened contrariety, and there being ſuch a contrariety be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and the world, it cannot be but that God ſhould haue many enemies, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ </seg>3</label> 3. That which maketh a thing ſo, is more ſo, if a man loath a bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker or veſſell becauſe phiſick hath been in it, he loatheth the phiſick much more, and if the world hate the godly becauſe they are godly, then they hate God much more, now the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue many enemies and that for this reaſon becauſe they are godly, therefore God himſelfe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6902:6"/> hath more.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rea. </seg>4</label> Further when two are at a great diſtance and neither doe yeeld, buckle nor comply to, or with one another, there muſt needes be a greate enmity: now ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt you cannot loue God and Mammon, you muſt loue the one and hate the other, God will haue no complying: and for this reaſon the Senate of Rome, as the Hiſtorians giue it, would not acknowledg Jeſus Chriſt to be a God, becauſe he is ſuch a one, (ſaid they) as if we acknowledg him to be God, he will not let us acknowledge other Gods, other Gods will comply &amp; be content we ſhall acknowledg others alſo, but for this Chriſt, if we acknowledge him we muſt acknowledge none other, now God is very
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6902:6"/> incomplying in all his wayes therefore certainly God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe muſt needs haue many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; &amp; very deadly: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Hence we may ſee that it is no ſtrange and new thing for us that are the people of God to meete with enemies: why should we be diſcouraged though we meete with enemies? Are we better then our Lord and Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? shall God himſelfe haue many enemies, and shall we thinke to haue none? It was <note place="margin">Inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo</note> the complainte of a heathen man, I haue enemies, his friend ſtanding by gaue him this anſwere, but that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s worſe that thou haſt no frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, though <note place="margin">ſed pejus eſt quod a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micos non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes.</note> a man haue many enemies, yet if he hath ſome faithfull friends he may comfort himſelfe thus, though I haue moſt bitter and vile enemies, yet I haue as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6902:7"/> faſt &amp; ſure friends: ſo that here is a further argument to shore up our unbeleeuing harts God himſelfe hath many enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obje. </seg>
               </label> But my enemies are ſuch as doe pretend friendship:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> And truely ſoe are Gods enemies ſuch as doe pretend loue. I pray you tell mee, I put it to your owne hearts: who are thoſe that doe pretend more loue to God then the breakers of the ſecond commandement, that doe make images? and wherefore doe they ſoe: Say they we will haue an image of Chriſt, whereſoeuer we become, that we may always be put in mind of Chriſt, what a mighty pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of loue is here, &amp; yet the breakers of the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement are ſaide to be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God: it is not ſaide ſoe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6902:7"/> of the breakers of any of the other commandements that they are haters of God, but of thoſe that breake the ſecond commandement: viſiting the iniquity of the fathers vpon the children unto the third &amp; fourth generation of them that hate mee: ſoe that though they pretend moſt loue yet they are the moſt haters.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obje. </seg>2</label> But for my enemies the Lord knoweth I haue done them no wrong but good:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Anſ. I pray you hath not God done good unto his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? God hath many ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? and what hurt hath God done them? Haue you ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? God hath ſoe: Haue you many enemies? God hath ſoe: Haue you many falſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies God hath ſoe: remember this doctrine, God
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6902:8"/> himſelfe hath many enemies: the ſecond obſeruation is,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>As the Lord hath many ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſoe he is pleaſed for a time to ſleepe un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his enemies:</hi> he ſleepeth, therefore it is ſaide here ariſe: ariſing is oppoſed to ſleeping, Lord why ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 44. 23.</note> thou? but what is that? not that we should underſtand it literally, for ſo the Prophet derided Baals Prieſts; cry aloud it may be your God <note place="margin">1. <hi>King</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 27.</note> ſleepeth: but underſtand it metaphorically: A man is ſaide to be a ſleepe when he is ſo intenſe about one buſines that hee doth not regard another, that buſines which hee doth not meddle with he is ſaide to be a ſleepe to: ſoe now when God shall haue many enemies, and they shall blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme his name and reuile his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6902:8"/> people, and hinder his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances: and God shall be deafe to all their blaſphemies reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and all their wickedneſſe when they shall perſiſt in evill and bring their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cked deviſes to paſſe, and yet God shalbe as it were blinde to all their dealings, then God ſleepeth to the enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his enemies: would you know the reaſons?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Firſt</hi> of all, it may be the enemies are not yet great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for God to contend with: the Eagle doth not hunt after flies, and a lyon doth not harneſſe himſelfe to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile againſt a poore worme: it may be the malice of the enemy is not yet great enough, &amp; ſoe is not a ſitt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject for the greate indignation of the greate God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6902:9"/> God ſuffereth them, to go on that it might be a greater and a more full object to beare his indignation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Againe, therefore God ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth this and ſeemeth to ſleepe for a time: becauſe his people are not provoked e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough againſt their enemies, as it was with the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael that went againſt Beniamin &amp; fell before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> twice, if Iſrael had overcome them the firſt time, they would not haue beene ſoe provoked againſt them, to haue cutt them all of as they were, but being beaten by them twice: thereby they were provoked to their deſtruction, ſo God ſuffereth his enemies to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile and ſleepeth to the caſe of his people for a time, becauſe the harts of his people are not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6902:9"/> ſtirred enough againſt their enemies to cutt them of fully when that is done then God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waketh.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Again ſomtimes God ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth becauſe his people ſleep to him, and ſay ariſe to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els, They ſleep to him, It was the ſpeech of an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour when he was in priſon, Oh (ſaide he) when I was in my pallace, I hoped ſoe much in men that I neglected truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in God: but now I am in priſon, I may hope leſſe in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and truſt more in God: ſo it may bee there is a time when Gods people doe fall a ſleepe to God: hope to much in men, and not enough in God: Now ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Woe to him that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 19.</note> 
               <hi>ſaith to the ſtone ariſe,</hi> shall God ariſe to his people when
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6902:10"/> they ſay to the ſtone, ariſe? Shall God ariſe for his people when they ſit downe, and riſe not up themſelues? Brethren faith is prayer in the coales, &amp; prayer is faith in the fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e: now it may be mens faith doth not burne out enough, it burneth dark, they pray, but are not hot in prayer, they liue, but they do not liue out of themſelues in God enough, wherefore that God may awaken his people, he ſleepeth himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4,</label> 
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> ſomtimes it is for this end, becauſe the pit of his enemies is not yet digged: conſider that 94. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12. 13. <hi>Bleſſed is the man whome thou chaſteneſt O Lord, and teacheſt him out of thy law that thou mayeſt giue him reſt from the dayes of adverſity, untill the pitt be digged for the wicked,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:6902:10"/> there is a time when the pitt of the wicked is digging, and all that time Gods people may be in ſuffering, God ſuffereth the wicked to run away with the baite, and doth not yet draw them, becauſe they are not full on the hooke, but when they haue ſwallowed the hooke, then he will draw them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Hence we may ſee what the reaſon is many times why there is ſo much evill in the Churches, and why the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies preuaile ſo much, ſo long God is the ſtrength of the Churches, and our ſtrength ſleepeth ſomtimes upon all the afflictions of the Churches, we are apt to be much diſcouraged like the diſciples who whileſt our Saviour was in the ſtorme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſleep: they came running in all haſt to him, ſaying, careſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6902:11"/> thou not that we perish? ſo it is many times when a ſtorm ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth upon the Church, God ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to ſleepe, and wee run in haſt to God, and are apt to charge God: Lord careſt thou not that we perish, but peace peace, he ſleepeth only, he will awake shortly, you shall ſee it, and they shall feele it, for the third point tels us that.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Though God ſeem to ſleep, &amp; his enemies prevaile, yet there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s a time when they shall be ſcat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tered, and when God ariſeth they are ſcattered:</hi> there are twop arts in this doctrine, J will handle them ſeverally.</p>
            <p>Firſt. Though the enemies of the Lord do prevaile, and God ſeemeth to ſleepe, yet there is atime when they shallbe ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered: In that 68. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. You haue the ſame words tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6902:11"/> here: <hi>Let God ariſe, let his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies be ſcattered,</hi> in the follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing part of the Pſalme, 12. <hi>verſ. it is ſaid, King sofarmies did flee apace,</hi> in the Hebrew it is they fled they fled, fled is twice, why ſoe? That is, they did flee very haſtily, and they fled moſt confuſedly, they fled alwaies, they fled, they fled, noting the greatneſſe of the flight. Reaſons: </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rea. </seg>1</label> Firſt If it were not ſo how should God be honoured in the world: God is reſolved to recover his honour, his truth, and his juſtice out of the hands of the world: ſaith the Pſalmiſt <hi>He will wash his feet in the blood of the wicked, ſo that a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58 10.</note> 
               <hi>man shall ſay verily there is a reward for the righteous, verily he is a God that judgeth in the earth:</hi> But did they not know
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6902:12"/> it before that God ruleth in the earth? True, But men will not ſay al that for God alwaies which their hearts know; and the glut of proſperity often doth quench their knowledge, but when Gods judgements are abroad then men shall ſay (he doth not ſay godly men; but then men shall ſay) though they be but bare me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they shall ſay &amp;c. Oh it is a ſweete time when ungodly men shall own their owne principles, and if you look into the Pſalme, you <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ</hi> 68. 11</note> shall find when the enemies of the Church are deſtroyed, that God hath many prechers made that doe teach his praiſes, ſaith the Pſalmiſt ver. 12. <hi>The Lord gaue the word greate was the company of thoſe that published it: Kings of armies did flee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace, and she that tarried at</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:6902:12"/> 
               <hi>home devided the ſpoile.</hi> The words in the originall are very ſignificant and doe note two things: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt the word which you read company; in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew it is Army: great was the army of preachers; an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Preachers is a greate matter, nay it is a great matter to haue ſeven or eight good preachers in a great army, but to haue a whole army of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, that is glorious: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secon. It doth note out the heartines of this preaching Army, for the word <hi>(Nephesh</hi> ſoule) is to be underſtood as in that place of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> it is ſaid there <hi>The wordes or book of the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11,</note> which being in the femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine gender doth ſuppoſe <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesh</hi> and as if hee should ſay (as <hi>Vatablus</hi> hath it) the words or booke of him that hath a preaching ſoule or hart, or the words
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6902:13"/> of a preaching ſoule or hart, ſo here where it is ſaid great is the the army of preachers, the word being in the feminine gender, it is as if he should ſay, great is the army of preaching ſoules, whoſe very hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts with in them shall preach of the Lords workes, now my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren it is much to haue a prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching army, but if this army shall with hart &amp; ſoule preach of Gods praiſe, O that is a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thing: yet thus shall it bee when the enemies of God shall be deſtroyed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing God will not looſe all thoſe ſermons of his owne prayſes, in due time the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Church shalbe ſcattered.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rea. </seg>2</label> All the plots and projects of Gods enemies ly under a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6902:13"/> curſe, now the curſe ſcattereth, and the bleffing gathereth, when God bleſſed, then the people were gathered, when God curſeth, then they are ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered: you know when Jacob was to bleſſe his children, in ſteade of bleſſing Levi, he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ge.</hi> 49. 7</note> to pronounce a curſe u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them, that they should be ſcattered in Ifrael, ſurely it is a part of the curſe to be ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the enemies of God and of his people are alwayes under the curſe, and (as a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned holy divine of your owne hath it) they are never prayed for, but looke as it is with ſome graſſe that groweth upon the houſe toppe, though it bee higher then that which growes in the field, yet noe man prayes for it, or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6902:14"/> noe man ſaith, the Lord bleſſe it, but the graſſe and corne that growes in the field, the men that come by ſay; there is a good crop of corne the Lord bleſſe it, ſoe though wicked men and the enemies of the Church doe perke up higher then the reſt; yet they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver under prayer, but alwayes under the curſe; and therefore no wonder though they bee ſcattered:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rea. </seg>3</label> God will lay mens wayes upon their owne heades; the fish shall be boyled in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it lived in, and men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by the ſame way they walked in, therefore <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 59.</note> you shall ſee how ſin is anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the like punishment, the Pſalmiſt ſpeaking con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his enemies <hi>ver.</hi> 6. 7. <hi>They returne at evening they</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:6902:14"/> 
               <hi>make a noiſe like a dog and goe round about the city, behold they belch out with their mouth, ſwordes are in their lippes,</hi> that is, they revile, they jeare and ſcorn at the godly there is their ſin, now looke into the latter end of the Pſalme at the 14. verſ. you shall ſee their anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable punishment, <hi>And at evening they shall returne and make a noiſe like a dog, and go about the citie, let them wander up and downe for meate and grudge if they be not ſatisfyed</hi> as they went about the citie barking and making a noiſ like dogs ſo shall they go about the city howling like dogs, thus God will anſwer men in their owne kind: was not <hi>Adoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bezek</hi> punished in his owne <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jud.</hi> 1. 7</note> kind? Egipt in its own kinde? And the Iewes of old in their owne
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6902:15"/> now kind? this is Gods method ſtill, and therefore if you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the 8 <hi>Rev.</hi> and 9. cha. with the 16 <hi>of the Rev.</hi> You shall ſee that the trumpets and the vialls are alike, &amp; ſome take them to be all one; but the trumpets note out the time when the ſins are commited, and the vialls the time when the punishments are inflicted, but the evils mentioned in both are much alike, becauſe God proportioneth mens pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment to their owne ſins, now the ene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ies of the Church haue ſcatterd themſelves up &amp; down to do miſchiefe, how are the Jeſuits &amp; the locuſts of our time ſcattered up and downe in all places? they haue ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Gods people and they ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their owne ſinnes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they become, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6902:15"/> there muſt come a ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring time for themſelues alſo for that is equall.</p>
            <p>You will ſay doe wee not ſee the contrary? our eyes are witneſſes of the contrary, wee ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the people of God are ſcattered, but wee doe not ſee the enemies are ſcattered.</p>
            <p>It is true: Gods people are ſcattered, and truely it is the remainder of the curſe upon them, for which wee are to be humbled, though God provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des a place for us in the world yet certainly it is ſome part of the curſe to haue our names changed from Iſrael to Jezreel: this is Gods way, that what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uill hee doth afterward bring upon his enemies, hee doth many times, firſt bring it upon his owne friendes, by his and their enemies, he firſt ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6902:16"/> to them, then hee awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for them; but to anſwer; Gods people are often ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but though they be ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yet there is much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between their and the worlds ſcattering: The ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Gods children is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a bleſſing to them, the ſcattering of his enemies is a curſe and ſo it endeth, a plaine inſtance for it you haue in Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi, ſayeth Iacob <hi>Let them be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 29. 7.</note> 
               <hi>in Iacob and ſcattered in Iſrael,</hi> yet that prooued a great bleſſing, for the tribe of Levi being ſcattered among all the tribes, by that means all the tribes had preachers: ſo now it is in the ſcattering of the Saintes, though they b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſcattered into divers places, yet they are made thereby a bleſſing to many cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tries:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6902:16"/> hereby they carry truthes into other places; hereby they are cleanſed from their own filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, herby they learn to walk more humbly, herby they learn to dye daily to the world and outward comforts, herby they are weaned from their freinds and all naturall engagements; hereby they are made more conformable to Jeſus Chriſt, who was a ſtranger upon earth hereby they meete with many experiences, hereby they ſee many promiſes fullfilled, here by they enioy the ordinances of God in a purer manner then before, ſo that all their ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings are bleſſings to them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Though the people of God be ſcattered yet they are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered againe. <hi>For great shall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1. 11.</note> 
               <hi>be the day of Jezreel.</hi> yet more fully <hi>Ier</hi> 23 2 3 4 <hi>Therfore thus</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:6902:17"/> 
               <hi>ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord God of Iſrael againſt the Paſtors that feed my people, ye have ſcattered my flock &amp; dri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away &amp; haue not viſited them, Behold</hi> J <hi>will viſit vpon you the evill of your doing, ſaith the Lord, And J will gather the remnant of my flocke out of all countries whether I haue dri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven them, and will bring them againe to their foldes, and they shall bee f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uitfull and increaſe, and I will ſet up shephards over them which shall feed them, and they shall feare no more nor bee diſmayed, neither shall they bee lacking, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Yea they are therefore ſcattered that they may be better gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. 34. <hi>Ezek:</hi> 11. 17. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold I even I will both ſearche my sheepe and ſeeke them out as a shepheard ſeeketh out his flocke in the day</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:6902:17"/> 
               <hi>that hee is among his sheep that are ſcattered, thus ſaith the Lord God, behold I iudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene cattell and cattell, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the rammes and the hee goates,</hi> before their ſcattering the goates were mingled with the flock; upon their gathering, the goates were ſeparated: a good garment may be rip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped into pieces, that it may be better ſewed, good is that ſpeech of Auguſtine, He that <note place="margin">Qui tru cidat noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderat quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niat, Qui cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderat quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cat.</note> killeth conſidereth not how he ſlasheth and rendeth, but he that cutteth to cure, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth how he cutteth, or thus, Suppoſe a man be to cut two men; the one to cure him, the other to kill him, that man which he cutteth to cure, he conſidereth how he cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him, but he taketh no care how he ſlasheth him
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6902:18"/> whom he intendeth to kill, ſo doth God deale in the cuttings and ſcatterings of his own children, and the vile world: or thus, an army you know, may be ſcattered two waies, The Souldiers when they come from their trenches, every one goeth to his hutt, and the whole army is in ſome meaſure ſcattered and devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but in order, this is an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly ſcattering: but when they are routed, that is another ſcattering, wherin there is no order, Gods people are ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as thoſe that go to their huts, but the wicked are ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered otherwiſe, their ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is a full routing, that is never gathered, this is the punishment of the enemies of the Church, they shall be ſcattered.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:6902:18"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> If ſo: Hence we may ſee what a lamentable thing it is to be an enemy of God, this is the portion of all the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of God, they shall be ſcattered, lamentable is their condition therfore, that are Gods enemies. Brethren, God is the beſt friend, and the worſt enemy, if God be my friend, what though J haue many enemies? afflictions shall be all rated of in due time, as the dog is when he falleth upon a friend: if the dog fall upon a thiefe or an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, we let him alone, he hath leaue to worry him; when afflictions ſeaze upon Gods people, in dew time they are chidden of; but when they fall upon Gods enemies, they shall not be rated of, they they may worry them, and the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6902:19"/> venome of their teeth shall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in them to all eternity. the text ſaith <hi>as for thoſe mine enemies &amp;c.</hi> It is ſome griefe to be ſlaine before iuſtice, but before mercy it ſelfe, that is more grevious, it is ſome griefe to be ſlaine before thoſe that cannot help: but to haue help ſtand by and not help, that is moſt bitter, ſuch is Chriſt, he is our help, he is our mercifull high Prieſt, and yet he ſaith, <hi>As for thoſe mine enemies which would not that I should reign over them, bring</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 19 27</note> 
               <hi>hither and ſlay them before me,</hi> oh what a ſad thing it is to be Gods enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Quest.</hi> But who are thoſe enemies? </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You will all ſay thus, that if a man ſeeth the picture of another, and aſſoon
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6902:19"/> as hee ſeeth it, hee falleth a tearing of it, and the more like the picture is to the man, the more hee teareth it: ſurely this man was an enemy to him whom the picture is like unto, ſo when men shall fall a tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Gods people, and therefore becauſe they are godly, are not they enemies to God?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly. Conſider <hi>Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</hi> 68. 21. ther is a plain place to shew you who are Gods enemies, ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>But God shall wound the head of his enemies and the hairy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. 21.</note> 
               <hi>ſcalp of ſuch an one as goes on ſtill in his treſpaſſes.</hi> Such as go on ſtill in their treſpaſſes, are Gods enemies, there is no child of God but may and doth fall into ſin, he may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aile in his ſpeech, and in his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6902:20"/> practiſe, but it is the character <note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 19</note> of the <hi>world to ly in wickednes.</hi> and therefore know you ſuch an one as hath been a drunkard and a drunkard ſtill, a ſwearer, eight, nine, or ten yeares ago, and a ſwearer ſtill, a Sabbath-breaker, a lyer, an adulterer a great while agoe, and ſo ſtill, that man is an enemy, and in due time the Lord will wounde the hairy ſcalpe of ſuch a ruffian, for he is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly When men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure to heare of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well-fare, and good ſucceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Churches, and of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ordinances of God, that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſigne they are Gods enemies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man loueth to heare good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him that he loueth, if a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> loue God, he loueth to hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good of God, and all that b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:6902:20"/> longeth to him, of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and of all the ordinances, but when men heare of good newes of the Churches, and of the ordinances, and do ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly grudge, repine and wish it otherwiſe, theſe are now ſecret enemies, and will be open.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly. The Scripture phraſe telleth us who are Gods enemies: ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Lord make plaine thy way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 5. 8.</note> 
               <hi>my face, becauſe of mine enemies.</hi> in the Hebrew it is, <hi>Lord make plain thy way before me, becauſe of my obſervers,</hi> malicious obſervation is a ſigne of enmity, and therfore when men shall diligently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, and lay waite for the haltings of Gods people, and are glad to find any thing to raiſe a ſcandall, more rejoycing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6902:21"/> at the ſcandall, then greeving for the ſin: thoſe (as beaſtes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quitan quam famelici porci immer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt ſe, in ſterco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ra ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum et exjis delicias faciunt Luther in Gen.</hi> 9.</note> which ſeek for the excrements of men to nuzzle in them) are Gods enemies, and God is theirs</p>
            <p>Fiftly. Thoſe that hinder the great proceedings, that God hath in the world, are his enemies, In the reſtauration and rebuilding of the Temple, God had many enemies: Tobiah, Sanballat, and many others; how did it appeare? they did out of malice labour to make the work of God to ceaſe: ſo when men in their generations and times, shall <note place="margin">5 <hi>Nehem.</hi> 6. 1.</note> maliciouſly labour to cauſe the workes of God to ceaſe, and hinder the great procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, which God hath on foot in the world, theſe are enemies and none but ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6902:21"/> now God is and hath been working of many great workes in the world; if any mans heart tell him that he hath thus taken up armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, let him lay down his weapons, and humble himſelfe, for God will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue him, God is greater, and will break him; The ſecond part of the doctrine follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t theſe enenmies, when God ariſeth, are ſcattered; Gods riſing is the cauſe of their ſcattering.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt. When God ariſeth, then all his hoſt ariſeth, when a man riſeth, then all his cloathes ariſe: when the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ariſeth, all the accidents riſe; when the Prince in the Field ariſeth, all his Souldiers ariſe; when God ariſeth, then
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6902:22"/> all his followers ariſe, and when they ariſe the enemies fly, and ſo are ſcattered.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly Conſider but the nature of his enemies as they are deſcribed in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, they are compared to waxe before the fire, though <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 68. 2.</note> waxe may lye a while there and not melt whileſt the fire is not blown up, yet when the fire flameth, the waze melteth; they are compared to the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jude.</hi> 13.</note> waues of the Sea, that roare whileſt they are in the Sea, yet when they come to the shore, they break; they are compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſmoak, which though <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 68. 2.</note> it riſe like a dark cloud, yet is ſoon ſcattered and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the puffe of the wind; they are compared to vapors, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13 3.</note> miſts and clouds: which though they may ſeem to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6902:22"/> threaten the earth with ſome great ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, yet when the ſun ariſeth in its full heat, then are they ſcattered, ſuch waxe ſuch waues, ſuch ſmoake, ſuch vapours and miſts are the Lords enemies; ſoon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſcattered when he ariſeth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> But though it may be eaſy (in regard of Gods power) to ſcatter the enemies of the Churches; yet when we look upon the condition of the Churches, as they are in themſelues, their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is very difficult, it is an unlikly thing that the diſtreſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches should be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered as the matter now ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with them, when were the enemies of the Church more prevailing then now they are?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> So it muſt be; what
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6902:23"/> is more unlikely, then that a dead man who lieth upon the graues mouth, should be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up to life, and to ſuch life as to aſcend, and go up to heaven, yet ſuch is the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Church when it cometh; <hi>Reu.</hi> 11. 12. It was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 11 12.</note> a very unlikely thing, that Iudah should ever come out of Babilon, the Iewes did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of it, and therefore as a man that thinketh he shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver returne the way that he goeth, taketh no heed to his way, obſerveth not by what turnings, windings and marks he commeth: ſo were they in their journey and way to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon: wherfore ſaith <hi>Jeremy, Set thee up way markes, make</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jeremy</hi> 31. 21 <hi>and</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>thee high heapes, ſet thine heart towards the high way: even the way which thou wenteſt, turne</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:6902:23"/> 
               <hi>thee again oh virgin Iſrael: turn again to theſe cities &amp;c. For the Lord hath created a new thing in the earth, A wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man shall compaſse a ſtrong man:</hi> as if he should ſay thus, you think your ſeleus in a very weak and low condition, the enemy ſtrong, and you in their hands, well, but the time shall come, that a woman shall lay ſiedge to a ſtrong man: <hi>Faemina virum fortem Anguſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abit,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 1 18.</note> for that word read to compaſſe, in the Hebrew ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth alſo to compaſſe by way of Siedge, and that word read man (in your tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) ſignifieth a ſtrong man, and the ſence of all is, that thoſe which are as weak as women, shall beſet, incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe and beleaguer thoſe that are ſtrong and valiant men, but
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6902:24"/> we ſee no likelyhood might they ſay of this, No, it may be ſo, but ſaith God, <hi>I will do a new thing:</hi> but there is no meanes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It mattereth not, <hi>J will create a new thing:</hi> I that drew once the world out of nothing, will draw the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Churches alſo out of nothing: I will be a creating God to the Churches though they be never ſo low, was it not an unlikly thing for Peter to be delivered that very night <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 12. 5. 6.</note> when he was to die the next day; Firſt he was in cloſe priſon, Secondly he was faſt in chaines Thirdly he was there kept with Souldiers. Fourthly he had rough keepers to keep the priſon doores. Fiftly he had to go through the firſt and ſecond watch. Laſtly he
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6902:24"/> was to paſſe the i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on gate that leadeth into the citie, yet prayer conveyed him through all theſe parties of oppoſition, the Church prayeth and Peter commeth, but what is this to us? we may not expect mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles now. <hi>Anſ.</hi> yes, we even we are commanded to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſoules into the hands of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 19.</note> 
               <hi>God in well doing, as unto a faithfull creator:</hi> not as unto a redeemer only, but of a cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, who hath promiſed his creating ſtrength to ſupply us in our diſtreſſes, and therefore ſaith, into the hands of a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full creator; well then, though the afflictions of the Churches be never ſo great, let us not mourne as thoſe that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope, for God can do it with eaſe, and much facility: he is our creator he will do it
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6902:25"/> in truth, and in much faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe for he is our faithfull creator, into whoſe hands we are to commit our ſelues and the condition of all the Churches.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly. When God ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, then God appeareth; now the enemies of God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure the ſight of God; When Iohn the beloved diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſt (who had the honour to be truſted with the book of the Revelation) ſaw but one Angell. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 8. he fell downe and trembled: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2 2 8.</note> Iohn was a good man, he had not a guilty Conſcience, yet when an Angell did but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare: John falleth down, how shal men tremble when the great God shall appear, and they shall appeare before him in all their guiltineſſe, ſurely
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6902:25"/> they will tremble and feare then, and that their feare will end in ſcattering.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">uſe. </seg>
               </label> Beloved we may ſee what an eaſy thing it is for God to ſcatter the enemies of the Church, though the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Church be never ſo greate, and the condition of the Saintes be neuer ſo meane, Is it not an eaſy thing for a ſtrong man to riſe when hee is free and healthy: is it not an eaſy thing for fire to diſſolue the wax: Is it not an eaſy thing for a lion to teare the caull of a mans heart. What is more ſtrong then a lion, what more thin then the caull of a mans heart. And God hath ſaid it: <hi>I will rend the cawle of their</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ</hi> 13 8. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16. 9.</note> 
               <hi>heart and there will I devoure them like a lion:</hi> was it not an eaſy thing for Samſon in all his
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6902:26"/> ſtrength to breake thoſe cords and withs where with he was tyed, Ieſus Chriſt is our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Samſon, and though his body the Church be bound with the withs and cords of the Philiſtims, yet he can eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ariſe, cracke, and breake, them in pieces, though they be never ſo ſtrong, Is it not an eaſy thing for a man to open his hand, God openeth his hand and wee are ſatisfied, Is it not an eaſy thing for a man to ſet his face againſt another? God only ſetteth his face a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his enemies and they are ſcattered, O with what infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite facility can God helpe the church: if his ſervants had noe credit with him, or if hee could not help them but with much difficulty, there were room for our diſcouragments,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6902:26"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut it is not ſo he ſpeaketh the word only, hiſſeth, ſtampeth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſeth and wee are helped.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">vſe. </seg>2</label> In the Second place Hence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee what a neceſſity there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat wee should ponder, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bſerue the workes of God; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the iudgments of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord; in theſe great volums, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee may read much of God; when God ariſeth, then God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to bee ſeene, and ſeene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecially, when Gods enemies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re ſcattered, then hee ariſeth: Now there are three ſorts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eople that are too blame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere, as concerning the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation of the Lords workes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd his great iudgments, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſt are thoſe that the prophet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omplaines of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>when the hand</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26 11</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord is lif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed up on high <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey will not behold his Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> An other are thoſe that the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6902:27"/> Pſalmiſt ſtrikes at in the 2 pſa 10 verſ: <hi>Be wiſe therefore O yee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ,</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Kings verſe</hi> 12 <hi>kiſſe the ſonne leaſt hee bee angry and ye perish in the way,</hi> who ſeeing and obſeruing God fetching his ſtroke at a land or people, will not ſtand out of Gods way, and reach; the third ſorte are thoſe that degrade the workes of God and nickname them, ſaying they are none of Gods workes but workes of Satan, like the Jewes and Phariſes who when Lazarus was raiſed from the graue by a miracle would haue killed Lazarus out of ſpight to Chriſt, ſo theſe men when God hath wrought gloriouſly for the converſion of a poore ſinner, or the deſtruction of his vile enemies, doe what they can to put Gods worke to death,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6902:27"/> calling that hipocricy which is Gods grace, that obſtinacy which is good conſcience, and that chance which is Gods glory; But let all theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that one place in the Pſ. 28. 5. becauſe they regard not the workes of the Lord nor the operation of his hands he shall deſtroy them, and not build them up there is more in it then wee are aware of; who doth not deſire to be build vp; wherefore do many men of knowledg and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtudy and take ſo much paines wearing out their flesh, but that they may be built vp in name and credit, wherefore doe you trade vp and downe the world but that you may be built up in your eſtate, and what is that which men feare more then deſtruction; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6902:28"/> is finall ruine, now my brethren if the great workes of the Lord bee done before you and you do not obſerue th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, you cannot be built up, and if you will not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the operation of the Lords hands you shall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; Gods judgments will take hold on thoſe that will not giue heed to his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, a man may be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for not obſerving another deſtruction, it is a fearful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> iudgment to haue no judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and he hath no judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that doth not minde th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lords judgment, it is mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Character of the Saintes i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the latter times of the worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that they are able to ſing t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſong of Moſes the ſervant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God and the ſong of the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaying, <hi>Great &amp; marvelous a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 15 3. 4.</note>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:6902:28"/> 
               <hi>thy workes Lord God Almighty, iuſt and true are thy waies thou King of Saintes: who shall not fear thee O Lord and glorify thy Name, for thou onely art holy, for all Nations shall come and worship before thee, for thy Judgments are made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſti. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Queſt,</hi> But ſuppoſe evill befall other men, it may bee that it falleth out by common providence, how shall I ſay that God is riſen, &amp; to be ſeen, &amp; ſeen ſpecially in a judgment, and when may a judgment be ſaid to come in way of a judgment.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt when wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men are ſnared in the workes of their own hands, then God is ſeen, and ſeene ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. 16. <hi>The</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 9. 16</note> 
               <hi>Lord is known by the judgment hee</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:6902:29"/> 
               <hi>that he executeth, the wicked is ſnared in the worke of his own hands. Higgajon Selah:</hi> there is not ſuch a clauſe again, in all the whole ſcripture that J remember, you haue Selah in many places, but you haue not thoſe two wordes Higga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jon Selah in any other place: the word Higgajon commeth from the Hebrew word Hagah that ſignifieth to meditate, and Higgajon is <hi>Meditandum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquid,</hi> a thing worth our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, or as much as if he should ſay, this is a matter of ſpeciall meditation, that God is to be known by the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that he executeth, when the wicked are ſnared in the work of their own hands, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therefore wicked men begi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a work againſt the people o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, and it wheeleth abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:6902:29"/> upon their own heades, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they are taken and ſnared in their owne practiſes, then God is ſeen ſpecially, and known by the judgment that he excecuteth. Higgajon Selah.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Then God is ſpecially to be ſeen, when the iudgment lyeth beyond the reach of ſecond cauſes, and is greater then the ſtock of the ſecond cauſe c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n beare, Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſtrength was a judgment to the Philiſtines, How was God to be ſeen in that? yes, for Samſon was the ſtrongeſt man that ever was, yet his mother (when she was bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him) was commanded <hi>to drink no wine, or ſtrong drink,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudges</hi> 13. 4.</note> 
               <hi>nor to eat any unclean thing:</hi> (which alſo did include ſtrong meat) God would not haue
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6902:30"/> Samſons ſtrength imputed to the ſtrength of ſecond cauſes, out of the weak came ſtrong, the ſecond cauſe was not able to bear ſo ſtrong effect, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his ſtrength was their iudgment, their vexation, their ſcourge, and this their judgment lay beyond the reach of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſe, therefore was God ſeen herein apparently: where there is any thing of Gods creating power, there is God plainly to be ſeen, now where the effect lieth beyond the bounds of the ſecond cauſe, Gods creating power is ſeen for to raiſe that, and therefore if in any evils, which befall the children of men, the ſtrength of the ſecond cauſe cannot reach them, there you may ſay: Oh my ſoule here is Gods judgment, Gods plague,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6902:30"/> Gods hand, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re is God ſeen, and ſeen ſpecially, here God is riſen.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. When Gods judgments for mens ſin, do ſo find them out, as they are their owne blabs, their owne accuſers, their own condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and ſomtime their own executioners, then God is to be ſeen, and ſeen eſpecially: ſo with Judas, and many others it is written of Iulian the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata, (who raiſed an army a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Perſians, in the fight he was ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ucken, whether with an arrow or otherwiſe J ſay not, but) being ſorely woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he took a handfull of his own blood, and flung it into the aire, ſaying: <hi>Viciſti Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee,</hi> thou haſt overcome mee O Galilean: you haue many ſtories to this purpoſe in the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6902:31"/> book of Martirs, recorded by Maiſter <hi>Foxe:</hi> J will name but that one, of that vile wretch, who dealt ſo injuriouſly with the Martir <hi>James Abbes,</hi> who after all his baſe uſage of that good man, was taken with a ſtrang kind of Phrenzy, and cryed out Iames Abbes is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and I am damned, Iames Abbes is ſaved and I am dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſo died: others were not privy to all his injuries, but his owne guilt made him his own blab, ſo now when a mans ſin commeth, and areſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him, and his heart and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is upon the rack conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, he burſting out into hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous outcries, being his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer, his own condemner, or his owne executioner, there God is ſeen, and ſeen appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:6902:31"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 4. Further when the worke of the Lord is carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſuch a ſtrong hand, as cannot be reſiſted, there God is ſeen: <hi>I will worke, and who</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jſa.</hi> 43 13</note> 
               <hi>shall let ſaith God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 5. Then a judgment commeth in way of a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when it maketh way to a further judgment, as when God giveth in mercy, he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth that he may giue, ſo when he ſmiteth injudgment, he ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that he may ſmite, he mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth way to his anger, when he is angry indeed, and when you ſee this: then ſay, here is God ſeene and ſeene eſpecially, now God is riſen, Bleſſed are all they that truſt in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> But how shall we raiſe God, that he may be ſeen in the world, for the good of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6902:32"/> the Churches?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The next point tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth us: <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>4</label> Our prayers doe excite, raiſe, and ſtir up God to the ſcattering and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our enemies; I will not ſpend much time in the proof of this; you all know the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the unjuſt judge, and you all know the promiſe of the juſt God, to heare prayer: Brethren, is God able to ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his enemies? Is God migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Is God all ſufficient? Hath God power enough to do it? God is pleaſed to make over his power, his wiſdome; his mercy to our prayers, who doth not know what credit prayer hath in heaven, and what ſtrength in e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rth, the truth is, prayer may do any thing that is reaſonable with God; And if you aske prayer by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6902:32"/> what authority it doth all, it will shew you its commiſſion in that place: 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 7. 1. 2 compared with 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 6. Where God wrought a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, to shew that he would anſwer prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Quest.</hi> But you will ſay, can any prayer do this, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite, ſtirre up and awaken God?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. No; But it muſt be a crying prayer, if vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence be offered to a man in his houſe, and he doth not cry for helpe, helpe commeth not in preſently, but if there be the eues in the houſe, and he putteth his head out at win<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dow, and cry murder, murder, men will breake up the dores, and come in preſently.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Beſides, they muſt be ſelfwakening prayers,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6902:33"/> that prayer will neuer waken God, that doth not waken your ſelues, and that prayer will neuer ſtirre and raiſe God, that do not ſtirre and raiſe your owne ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly It muſt be a ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying prayer, you know the caſe betwene Moſes, and Iſrael Iſrael had prouoked God, God ſayes to Moſes, that hee <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo:</hi> 32 10: 14.</note> 
               <hi>would conſume Iſrael, and raiſe up him, to bee a greate people.</hi> Moſes layes by all that, and he goes to God in prayer, and what arguments doth hee uſe, his prayer was but short, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d all the arguments were fetched from God, and the covenant, remember thy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant <hi>with Abraham, and thou art a mercifull God, ſlow to anger.</hi> &amp;c. not a word of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, it was a ſelf-denying pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6902:33"/> and was heard preſently, in prayer, thoſe arguments take moſt with God, that are from God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly Beſides it muſt be a continued prayer: as Col: 4: 2: prayers are the Saints fact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, and negotiate for them in heauen, therefore they muſt ly by it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly it muſt be where the man abideth in Chriſt, and Chriſt in him 15. Iohn. <hi>If y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 15</note> 
               <hi>abide in mee, and my words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in you, yee shall aſke what you will, and it shall bee done unto you:</hi> he doth not ſay if you abide in an tauerne or in an alehouſe, or in ſuch a vile courſe, but <hi>If ye abide in mee, and my wordes abide in you, then ye shall aske.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly Reforming prayers are moſt preuailing <hi>Virtutes ſunt</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:6902:34"/> 
               <hi>orationis fundamenta</hi> there is no energy in thoſe prayers that are not ſtrengthned with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, either your prayers will eat up your ſins, or elſe your ſins will make a hand of your prayers Iſai. 58. 6. <hi>Looſe the bands of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. Then shalt thou call and the Lord shall anſwer, thou shalt cry, and he shall ſay here am I; if thou &amp;c.</hi> Though the leſſon be never ſo good, yet if the inſtrument be out of tune, there is no harmony, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious prayer is very ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding therefore.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Laſtly Jt muſt be joynt prayers, when the Church prayed, Peter was delivered. it is trve that their prayer was very urgent in it ſelfe, for according to the Originall i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is, they continued in out-ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6902:34"/> prayer, it was holding prayer, for they continued, it was ſeaſonable, for it was the night before his appointed death, yet withall the Church prayeth, and Peter commeth, one ſtring doth not make the harmony, and the word is, <hi>If two or three of you shall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 16.</note> 
               <hi>make a Symphony Mat.</hi> 18. 19 <hi>It shall be done for you:</hi> God that is overcome by none, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth <note place="margin">Deus qui nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perari poteſt precibus ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Hieron.</note> himſelf to be overcome by prayer, but your prayer muſt be full of himſelfe, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and a cloſe leaguer, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all you lie perdue, keep Centinell, or to ſpeak in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture phraſe <hi>Iſay</hi> 62. 6. 7. All you that are watchmen upon the wals of Ieruſalem, all the day and all the night continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, ceaſe not, ye that are mindfull of the Lord, keepe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6902:35"/> not, ye that are mindefull of the Lord, keepe not ſilence, And giue him no reſt, till he repaire, and untill he ſet up Ieruſalem the praiſe of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Vſe</hi> Will prayer do it? Will prayer raiſe God, for the ſcattering of the enemies of the Churches? J beſeech you in the name of God, let us conſider where to lay the fault, and the blame of much of that evill, which is come upon the Churches, in theſe latter times when the defeate was lately before Antwerpe there was fault laid on ſuch a man, and ſuch a man, when we conſider the afflictions of Germany, we are ready to ſay, if ſuch a King or country had ſtepped in, all this evill had been prevented, the Palatinate
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6902:35"/> reſtored, and peace ſetled, but may we not rather ſay, if our prayers had ſtepped in, This word telleth us, that our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers do awaken God, and when God is awakened, then the enemies are deſtroyed, we ſee then in truth where the fault lyeth, our prayers haue not come in full enough, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the leſſe we haue prayed before, the more let us pray now, pray in your cloſets, pray in your families, pray in the aſſemblies, pray alone, pray in company, pray for all the Churches, pray for Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, the firſt place of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, pray for Holland your hiding place, and in all your prayers forget not England, ſtill pray for England, take ſome motiues,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt You are unnaturall,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6902:36"/> if you pray not; it is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Croeſus his ſonne, that hee was dumbe: and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one about to kill his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though he had been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies dumb before, yet then he burſt forth into this ſpeech, what will you kill Croeſus? If you be in Chriſt, the Church of Chriſt is more to you then many Croeſuſſes; your grace doth not extinguish nature, but advance it, helpe, and not hinder, a gracious heart can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be unnaturall though it loveth to be ſupernaturall.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly It is the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a good Chriſtian, and of true grace, to obſerue what worke God is doing, and to helpe on that worke: what God is doing in the world, and to help that on, what God is doing upon his own heart, and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6902:36"/> to helpe that on, Oh Lord ſaith the ſoule, helpe mee, I will help thee; I will put my shoulder unto thy worke, as thou art pleaſed to put thy hand to my duty; now the great work which God is do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in theſe times, is the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out of the ſeven vials, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. and if you look into the <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 8. You shall finde that the ſaints prayers are their vials, help forward then Gods vials, with your viall, viall doth call for viall.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly Either good and deliverance will come unto the Churches or els it will not; if it do not, you had need pray that your hearts may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in all and ſetled, prayer is a compoſing duty, and fully ſetling, if it doe come, you had neede pray that you may
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:6902:37"/> haue the comfort of it, when it commeth, or els that you may not envy at thoſe that haue prayed, for it is a hard thing for one that ſtandeth Idle, not to envy at him that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly You do not loue the Churches if you doe not pray for them: <hi>He that loveth Ieruſalem, prayeeh for the peace of Jeruſalem:</hi> Doe you loue England? Doe you loue Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many? Do ye loue Holland? Doe you loue the Churches, and your friends? He that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth Ieruſalem, prayeth for it, and if you doe not pray for them, you haue no loue to them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly You cannot proſper if you do not pray, they shall proſper that loue thee: how loue thee? in praying for thee,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6902:37"/> you cannot proſper if you pray not for the Churches, will you not pray then?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly you are not Gods ſeruants, if you doe not pray for his ſervants; you are not Gods children, if you pray not for his children, if you mark that of the Pſalmiſt; it is made an act of ſervice, and a ſigne of a ſervant, <hi>to pitty the duſt and ſtones of fallen Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> ſaith he, thy ſervants pitty the duſt therof, as if they were not ſervants that haue no pitty, I know you would not haue your livery taken from you, all things of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſympathize with one auo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if you haue the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with the Saintes, you shall, you will, you muſt ſympathyze with them in all conditions you cannot but
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:6902:38"/> pray.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seventhly You cannot haue a part in the prayers of the Churches, unleſſe you pray for the Churches, think upon this argument, can you be contented to looſe your share in all the prayers of the Saintes, an action there, is better then an action in the Eaſt-India company, there ſtock is great, if your ſtock go not in, you cannot haue a part with them, and that is evill.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Eightly If you pray not for the Churches your own ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish prayers will be bootleſſe, when a man shall pray much for his owne family, his own name, or eſtate, his owne child that lieth a dying, and will not pray for the dying Churches, this is a ſelf-ish du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:6902:38"/> a carnall ſelfe-ish ſpirit is very loathſome in what is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, and what are you the better for your rich cabbin, your warme cabbin, your neate cabbin, if your ship ſinke.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Ninethly Conſult with the 13 chapter of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 1. 2. There you find it writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 13 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>that the Ammonite and the Moabite should not come into the Congregation of God for ever:</hi> what was the reaſon? <hi>becauſe they met not the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael with bread and with water.</hi> He that will not meet with diſtreſſed Iſrael, with ſuch reliefe as he may, is an unfit man to haue a name in a Church of Chriſt, and it is unfit he should come into the houſe of God for ever, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as ever you deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to haue
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6902:39"/> a name in Gods houſe, pray, pray, oh now pray, you may with this bread and water meet with Iſrael, and in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with them, you do meet with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Tenthly The price of the welfare peace, and good of the Churches is now riſing, <note place="margin">Fugian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quimur.</note> the time may come it may not be purchaſed or bought in by prayer. J remembcr I haue read of a man that brought the booke of the Sibils unto the Emperour or King of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, and deſired a great price for thoſe books, the Emperour refuſed, he goeth away, burneth halfe the books doubled the price, and then commeth to the Emperour, and offered him them at that rate, the emperour refuſeth again, he went away, and burnt
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:6902:39"/> the halfe of thoſe books which were left, and doubled the price, which the Emperour conſidering, gaue him the whole money which he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſo now it may be, you may haue the welfare, the peace, the life of the Churches for prayer, time may come wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in though you adde to your prayer, your eſtates, to your eſtates, your liberties, to your liberties, all your welfares, and to your welfares your lives, yet you may goe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, now it may bee had at this good rate, will you not take this good commodity whileſt it is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to you?</p>
            <p>Tenthly Jt may be the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe <note place="margin">10.</note> of the Churches ſtayeth upon your prayer, if that mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife would come away, the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:6902:40"/> woman would be delivered, <hi>Reu.</hi> 7. Foure Angels were <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 7.</note> ſent out to punish the world, and after that a fift Angel is commiſſioned to go bid them hold their hand, till the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the living God are ſealed in their foreheades: An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels work muſt ſtay, till they be ſealed ſaith Hezekiah. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 37 3. <hi>This day is a day of trouble,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 37 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and of rebuke, and of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, for the children are come to the birth, and there is not ſtrength to bring forth.</hi> So ſay I brethren, it may be the Lord your God will hear the words of all Rabſhakahs, whom the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the Church haue em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ployed to reproach the living God &amp; will reproue the words, which the Lord your God hath heard, wherefore lift up your p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>yer for the rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:6902:40"/> that are left, God ſaid to Moſes, let me alone, but to you otherwiſe, why doe you let me alone, I ſtay for you, if you pray earneſtly, I will come quickly.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Laſtly. I put you but this diſjunction, either oh Iacob thou haſt thy brother Eſau to meet withall, or elſe thou haſt not; if not, what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thy feares, If thou art to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32 24. <hi>and</hi> 33. 10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54 26. 17 58. 14:</note> meet with rough Eſau, then remember what one nights ſweating in prayer did, how it firſt obtained the face of God, then of Eſau, the promiſe is made to you, Jf every promiſe is a new foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtep for prayer, wherefore you that ever prayed, pray now, nay you that never prayed, pray now, now is a praying time, and it is good
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6902:41"/> pulling whileſt God is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, begging whileſt God is giving, and hath God dealt out nothing to the Churches in theſe laſt times? Doe but obſerue which way the wheele turneth, in theſe latter dayes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But why doe you exhort us to pray? we are here purpoſely, and come to pray.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, we are ſo, but we muſt pray at other times too, we are here this day to pray, that we may pray hereafter, that wee may ſet wheeles of prayer on going, prayer doth fit for prayer, but yet pray for the preſent, and ſo we come to the fift note.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> 5 When the people of the land go forth to warre, the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:6902:41"/> of the Lord should go forth to prayer, when the Arke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, then ſaid Moſes, Ariſe O Lord &amp;c. our prayers are to lead Armies into the field. 1. Iosh. 17. ſee how the people lead forth Ioshua, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as we hearkened unto Moſes in all things, ſo will we hearken unto thee, only the Lord thy God be with thee, as he was with Moſes. you know the prayer of Aſa, Iehosha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat, Hezekiah, and other worthies, to this purpoſe, reaſons of it, are theſe eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Every buſineſſe is to be led forth by prayer, prayer is a leading duty, to all our dut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, and the greater any buſineſſe is, the more prayer is to be made, the buſineſſe of warre is a great
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:6902:42"/> buſineſſe, almoſt miraculous, when I ſee an Army, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I ſee a company of walking Townes, it is a great matter, and will you not haue ſo great a buſineſſe led on by prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Object.</hi> But if a man haue a buſineſſe to do, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth haſt, by attending to prayer, he may looſe his buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For that purpoſe, conſider but that one place, in anſwer to this, <hi>Iosh.</hi> 5. 2. In the foregoing chapter the children of Iſrael went through Iordan and came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their enemies country, and in this verſe the Lord ſaid unto Joshua, <hi>Make thee sharpe knives, and circumciſe againe the children of Iſrael the ſecond</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioshua</hi> 5. 2.</note> 
               <hi>time,</hi> now upon their circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:6902:42"/> they were ſore, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore verſ. 8. it is ſaid, <hi>They abode in their places in the camp, till they were whole.</hi> Now being come through Iordan, and lying before Iericho, among all their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the natiues could not but heare that they were cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, and how ſore they were, inſomuch as the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael might haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected and ſaid, Oh Lord, if we be circumciſed, we shall hinder our deſignes, weaken our ſelues, advantage our enemies, that they may fall upon us in our trenches, but as the Lord commanded, ſo did they, they were circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, neither did this act of Religion hinder their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and therefore let none ſay, If I ſtay upon prayer,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:6902:43"/> my buſineſſe will take deſpair, No no, precedent prayer will make it proſper, truſt God, and you will finde it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Salamon ſaith, <hi>All things are beautifull in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3 1. 11.</note> 
               <hi>their ſeaſon: there is a time for all things:</hi> therfore a time for prayer, and though wee are to pray continually, yet there is ſomtime, wherein we are eſpecially to draw near to God; ſaith the Pſalmiſt: <hi>For this shall every one that is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 32 6.</note> 
               <hi>godly, pray unto thee, in a time that thou maieſt be found,</hi> Grace maketh one pray, the wiſdome of grace maketh one know the occaſion, ſeaſon, and time of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt Fearing times, are times of praying, ſaith the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:6902:43"/> Pſalmiſt; At what time I am afraid, J will truſt in thee, and true faith ſoon worketh it ſelfe into prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly Tropicall uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine times are times of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2. 3. Seek ye the Lord all ye meek of the earth, if ſo be that ye may be hid in the day of the Lords wrath, &amp;c. when the world labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth under uncertainty, then should the Saintes labour in prayer, Again the morning time is a time of prayer. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 5. 3. <hi>My voice shalt thou hear</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 5 3.</note> 
               <hi>in the morning, O Lord in the morning will I direct my prayer unto thee.</hi> There is a morning of every yeere, aſwell as a morning of every day: there is a morning to every buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, aſwell as a morning to every day; now is the yeeres
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:6902:44"/> morning, now is the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our great buſineſſe, wherefore now up in the morning of this great worke, let us direct our prayers to the Lord, and looke up, pray now my brethren, for now it is ſeaſonable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly; As the promiſe is the only hold that we haue on God, ſo prayer is the only ods that we haue of our enemy: Beloved the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies haue moſt commonly the outward advantage of Gods people, look upon both, and you shall find, that outwardly they haue much odds, either more men, more money, or more munition, what shall weigh downe this odds but prayer? Many times prayer doth more then the whole Army, conſider <hi>Pſ.</hi> 76. 3 <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 76 1.</note>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:6902:44"/> 
               <hi>There brake he the arrowes of the bow, the sheild, the ſword, and the battaile:</hi> where? In Salem, Jn Sion, He doth not <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 2</note> ſay in the field, the arrowes are firſt broken in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies by the Saintes prayers, after that in the field by the Lords Souldiers, It is ſaid of Archimeder being a Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matician, that he did more by drawing his lines, then any other Souldier did by his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, ſo Gods people may do more by the lines they draw, and the prayers they make, then others can do any other way, prayers are the Saintes ſcaling ladders where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they leap over wals, and their ſtrength whereby they break through hoſtes, you know uſually there is much diſorder in Armies; the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:6902:45"/> haue much evill and ſin among them, though the Souldiers be outwardly ſtrong yet many of them are inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weak, and prayer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in to gather up the weak forces, Numb. 12. 15. you may ſee how that for the ſin of one woman, the whole hoſte of Jſrael was ſtaide, and could not march on, her ſin hindred their march, shee was but one, and a woman, it may ſeem therfore ſtrang that the whole body of the Army should ſtay upon her, yet ſo it was, and they could not remooue till prayer came in: <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>Moſes cryed to the Lord ſaying, heale her now O God J beſeech thee.</hi> Then she was healed, and the people iourneyed, thus prayer orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the rankes, fetcheth up
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:6902:45"/> the weak forces; leadeth on the Army upon the enemy, and commeth in the reare, without prayer then; there is no footing, we are not fit to ſtrike till our armes be in ioynt, and prayer iointeth us, we are not fit to be exalted, till we be humbled, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er humbleth us, and if it be ſo, then by way of uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Vſe</hi> You may ſee what worke we haue to do this day, we are to lead forth this well formed Army, as you heard in the mandate, ſent unto us by the States, of a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed leaguer, under the command of that Noble and worthy Generall, the Prince of Orange, and mee-thinks he doth as it were put prayer in office, and ſaith, I will not
<pb n="0" facs="tcp:6902:46"/> be commander, prayer, shall, J will be only Lieutenant unto prayer, let prayer goe firſt, let prayer ſtrike the firſt ſtroke mee-thinkes I hear a dialogue and conference betweene him and the country, wee deſire you Sir to take the care of this great Army, wee commit it to your wiſdome, goe and proſper, but ſaith he, I dare not goe untill prayer goe, J am under prayer, giue mee prayer firſt, and then I will go, firſt ſmite with your pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and then wee will ſmite with our weapons, ſmiting prayers are now expected, and though there are divers mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues which I haue uſed to ſtir up your heartes, to pray for the Churches in generall, yet take three or foure more, which may haue ſome ſpeciall
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:6902:46"/> relation, unto this people and you amongſt them. </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt The enemies which <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sicut paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es ſpir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis &amp; ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ad predi candum elegit, ita aſta tos et du plices Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtus ad falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumet. Greg mor. lib</hi> 12. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> you pray againſt are the moſt wicked enemies that God hath of all enemies thoſe are moſt wicked that are moſt crafty, the artificial ſinner is the worſt ſinner, (as the naturalized grace is the moſt gracious) ſuch are the Antichriſtian ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Church, for as (Gregory obſerveth it) Ieſus Chriſt did chuſe ſimple poore men to preach the truth, ſo Antichriſt chuſeth thoſe which are crafty, ſubtill to diſperſe errors, of all enemies thoſe are moſt vile, which are moſt cruell, and thoſe are moſt cruell unto the Churches, that haue once made profeſſion of the truth, &amp; proved Apoſtates, the Scripture pointeth at three
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:6902:47"/> eſpecially in this particular, the Devill, the Iewes, and Antichriſt, the Deuill is cruell unto mankind, he is the grand Apoſtate, the Iew is cruell unto all Chriſtians, he is a vile Apoſtate, Antichriſt is cruell to all the preſent Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and he is a greate Apoſtate, yea not onely an Apoſtate, but Apoſtacy in the abſtract. 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 3. and therefore cruelty it ſelfe: in the book of the Revelation, Rome and the Antichriſtian party is called Sodome, it is called Egypt, and it is called Babilon: you know the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſſe of Egypt, the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of Babilon, and the vilany of Sodome vnto Gods people, why should Rome and the antichriſtian party ſtand under all theſe names, but becauſe
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:6902:47"/> they are guilty of all their evils, and the worſer they are, the more hold you haue on them to pray againſt them, Arrius was a vile enemy to the Churches, and ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ciuell, yet he was deſtroyed, how ſo? Hiſtorians tell us, <hi>Orationes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus fuit, non morbi,</hi> his death was the work of prayer, not of his diſeaſe, ſuch effects may your prayers haue, what ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble can ſtand before the flame of prayer, Oh that our heartes were much inflamed in this great ſervice.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly conſider you are here in your poſſeſſions, in your lot, hidden when others of your brethren are not come to their lot, mark that place in the 3 Deut. Reuben, Gad, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 18. 20.</note> and the half tribe of Manaſſeh, were come into their lot, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:6902:48"/> inheritance, before the reſt of the Children of Iſrael, What then, should they ſit downe quietly? No, at the 18 verſ. they were not to ſit downe, but they were to paſſe over armed before their brethren, ſo God haueing provided for you, before many of your deare brethren, and his good people, you are not now to ſit downe quietly in your own lot, but to go up armed before the reſt of Gods people, and prayer is your beſt harneſſe. </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly You are here on purpoſe to pray, it is the end why you are come hither, that you might haue liberty to pray, J am loath to ſpeak it, I would I might not, you had praying liberty denied to you, when any met together in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:6902:48"/> to pray, you know it was theirs and your reproach, this place is your Gilgall, wherin the Lord hath rowled away that reproach from you, Oh that your liberty might not degenerate into licence, you haue now praying liberty and if this be the thing you are come for, and now you haue ſuch an oppertunity, will you not improue it, if a man leaue one place of trading, that hee may ſet up his shop wirh more freedome in another, and in the ſecond place money be brought unto him, will hee refuſe to take money? this is your caſe, you could not haue ſo free a trade for heaven as you deſired, here you haue leaue to open your shops, and behold this day a praying op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertunity, which I call money,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:6902:49"/> is put into your hands, will you refuſe it, Conſider you are come on purpoſe to pray.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly in all likelyhood this country shall be hidden, and you shall not looſe your pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, I will tell you what Mr. Brightman ſaith, whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory is ſweet and precious, he ſayeth, there are three ſorts of reformed churches, the firſt the German, the ſecond, the French, the Sweedish the Scottish, and Holland, the third the English, which are all different, for the English is ruled by prelates, the French, the Scotish, Swedish and Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is turned by presbyters the German hold conſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, and other things which other reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches do not, Germany there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:6902:49"/> he compared to Sardis, and thence foretold all the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t haue come up on it. Holland, Swethland, Stotland, and the French he compared to Philadelphia, and ſayeth though they haue but a little ſtrength, and the houre of temptation shall come, and ſome shall labour to shut their doore, yet none shall shut it, it is the rather to bee conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, becauſe he foretold the evils that came upon Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and why may he not ſpeak true in this alſo, and then who would not pray for this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſeeing that he may not looſe his prayers? wherefore I intreat you in the Name of God, now up and be doing, ariſe; O daughter of Sion, ariſe O he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rts of the people of God that God might ariſe, and his
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:6902:50"/> enemies might be ſcattered, awake, awake, and now up to prayer.</p>
            <p>Queſt. You will ſay to me we are agreed, wee muſt go to prayer, both now and at home; but what shall wee ſpeak, that God may ariſe and that his enemies may be ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt Bring forth the Lords engagements, and tell him how much hee is engaged to helpe the Churches, the Lord ſaith in his word, that Babilon shall fall, for ſtrong is that God <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 8. <hi>Pſ</hi> 121. 4. 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 6. 34. 35</note> that hath condemned her: <hi>the Lord ſaith, He never ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth nor ſleepeth,</hi> the Lord ſayeth in his word; <hi>If his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple pray when they goe forth to warre, he will hear and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their cauſe,</hi> goe and tell God; Lord thou haſt ſaid thus
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:6902:50"/> and thus, thou haſt ſaid thou wilt neither slumber, nor sleepe, thou haſt ſaide thou wilt maintaine thy cauſe, Oh then, ariſe O Lord, and let thine enemies be ſcattered.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the ſecond place. Tell the Lord how long hee hath ſeemed to ſleep; and that the time appointed for the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches deliverance is now at hand, ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Jt is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119 126.</note> 
               <hi>time for thee Lord to work, for they haue made void thy Law,</hi> and again, <hi>Haue mercy upon Zion, for the time to fauour her,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 102 13. 14.</note> 
               <hi>yea the ſet time is come, for thy ſervants take pleaſure in her ſtones, and favour the duſt thereof:</hi> this is the reaſon why the time is come, ſo go to God and tell him; Lord thou haſt ſtood ſtill a greate while, oh now the time is come, men
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:6902:51"/> haue made void thy law; the Saintes pitty the duſt and take pleaſure in the ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of the waſted churches, it is time for thee to riſe. <hi>Ariſe O Lord.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Further, Tell the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d that the enemies are up already a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly, tell him that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere long he will riſe though you do not pray; Lord if wee should never pray, woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou helpe the Churches? a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d wilt not thou ariſe a little the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for our prayers? wherefore <hi>Ariſe O Lord,</hi> &amp;c. </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly Tell the Lord that all things are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dy; it is an argument that God moveth us with to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e in to him, Lord we uſe thine owne argument, Lord Ariſe all things are now ready, when the wind is good, &amp; when the ſervants of the ship are ready, and haue got their
<pb facs="tcp:6902:51"/> ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kling all ready, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor is up, onely the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſter is not come into the ship, they will ſend one to tell him, Sir the wind is good, your ſervants are ready, and the ship is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſayle, we pray you come away, ſo tell the Lord that all his people are up at prayer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting him; and all the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Gods people are ſpread; and their heartes under ſayle, and nothing can be done till the Maſter come; untill God himſelfe come; come therefore O Lord; come away; <hi>Ariſe O Lord &amp; let thine enemies be ſcattered.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:6902:52"/>
            <p>After this Sermon began to be printed, ſomthing was added, the reſt was taken by Charact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, whileſt it was preached.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:6902:52"/>
            <head>Faults eſcaped in the Printing.</head>
            <p>pag. 5. l. 25. read. Theſe. p. 12. l, 1. for ſo that read but p. 18. l. 6. r. flame r. p. 20. l. 5. r. are apt. &amp; l. 12. r ſeemeth. p. 25 l 2. r. bleſſing. p. 28. l 1. r. owne p. 29. l. 5. r. contrary. &amp; l. 21. r. be. p. 30<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> l. 4. 5. &amp; 7. r hereby. p, 42. l 12. r. waxe, p. 45. In the margent for Pſ, 1, 18, read, Ier 31, 22, p: 58 l 5. r this p. 93. l. 9. r prayer &amp; l. 19, r, at a window<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p. 65. l 14. r. mee. &amp; l. 18. r. a tauerne p; 66. l. 1 r fundamenta. p. 67. l. 17 r. you that ly p. 67, &amp; 68, r ye that are mind. full of the Lord keepe not ſilence but once. p, 73. l. 19. r one another. l 76. in the margent r. fugientia l. 77 l. 21 r. for tenthly eleventh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. p. 79. l 18 blot out Jf p 80. l. 21. r. firſt p. 81 l 1 r people of the Lord p 84 l 24 r prayer. l. 87. l. 10 r Archimedes p 88. l 6. r. gather vp. &amp; l. 14. r ſtrange. p 90 l 17 r our p. 91 in the margent for ſpiritis r. ſpiritus &amp; for aſtatos r, aſtutos. p. 93. l, 6 r very &amp; l 8 r o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationis p. 93. l. 11. &amp; 24. r orportunity. p. 96. l. 20. r for turned governed.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
